Now, when you think of it,
使徒パウロは
とても謙遜な人でした
the apostle Paul was a very humble man.
He was flexible.
そして 柔軟な人でした
He says: “To the Jews I became as a Jew,”
“ユダヤ人に対しては
ユダヤ人のように—”
and “to those under law
I became as under law.”
“律法のもとに
ある人たちに対しては—”
ある者のように” なりました
But there were limits to Paul’s flexibility,
だからといって どこまでも
柔軟だったわけではありません
and we’re going to talk
about that in just a few moments.
この点について考えてみましょう
First of all, though,
when Paul came down to Jerusalem,
パウロがエルサレムに来ると
そこの長老たちがこう言います
the elders explained that thousands of Jews
had become believers
“幾万人ものユダヤ人が
信者になりましたが—”
and they were all zealous for the Law.
“彼らはみな
律法に対して熱心です”
Now, they’d heard a rumor about Paul.
“それから こんなうわさがあります”
They’d heard the rumor
that Paul was telling the Jews
“あなたがユダヤ人に—”
“子どもに割礼を施さないよう
教えているとのことです”
not to circumcise their children,
and the elders were worried about it.
事態を憂慮した長老たちは
ある提案をします
They had a plan.
We read about that plan in Acts chapter 21,
その提案は
使徒 21章に書かれています
if you would like to turn there,
Acts 21:23, 24.
使徒 21章23, 24節を
読んでみましょう
Here’s their plan:
“So do what we tell you:
“ですから わたしたちが告げる
このことをしてください”
“We have four men
who have put themselves under a vow.
“わたしたちのところには
誓約を立てた四人の人がいます”
“Take these men with you
“この人たちを連れて行って
一緒に儀式上の清めをし—”
“and cleanse yourself ceremonially
together with them
“その費用の世話を見て—”
“and take care of their expenses,
“彼らが頭をそってもらえるように
してやりなさい”
“so that they may have
their heads shaved.
“Then everyone will know
that there is nothing
“こうすればだれもが—”
“あなたについて聞かされている
うわさには何の根拠もなく—”
“to the rumors
they were told about you,
“but that you are walking orderly
“あなたが秩序正しく歩んで—”
“自らも律法を守っていることを
知るでしょう”
and you are also keeping the Law.”
この前の部分はパウロが—
Now, it says they have heard
a rumor about you,
子どもに割礼を施さないようにと
教えている—
that you were telling Jews
not to circumcise their children.
といううわさについて述べています
Paul was probably not telling Jews
パウロがそのように教えた
とは思えません
not to circumcise their children.
なぜならパウロは
ユダヤ人をつまずかせないために—
As has already been mentioned,
Paul took Timothy and circumcised him
テモテに割礼を施したことさえ
あったからです
so as not to stumble the Jews.
Paul realized that there was nothing wrong
割礼それ自体は 間違っていないと
パウロも承知していました
with circumcision per se.
It was when people
proclaimed that circumcision
割礼が救いに不可欠だと
主張するのが問題でした
was necessary in order to gain salvation
that the problem arose.
ですから それは
根拠のないうわさでした
So this was a rumor.
But some brothers and sisters
were willing to believe a rumor
ところが ある兄弟姉妹は
忠実なパウロを信じるのではなく—
about a faithful brother
rather than to trust Paul.
うわさを信じてしまいました
Just as today, some believe
everything they read in the newspaper
現代でも 新聞の情報すべてを
うのみにする人がいるのと同じです
and they don’t even ask any questions.
So now here’s the question:
こういう状況でしたので
長老たちはパウロにある提案をします
What were they going to do about it?
The elders had a suggestion.
They said: “We have four men
who have put themselves under a vow.”
“わたしたちのところには誓約を立てた
四人の人がいます” と言っています
And they wanted Paul
to take these men to the temple
そしてこの四人を神殿に連れて行って
費用を払うようにと言います
and pay their expenses.
Paul agreed.
パウロは承諾します
Now, that took humility.
これは謙遜さの求められることでした
We all know how strongly Paul felt
about keeping the Law,
パウロは律法に関しては
はっきりした考えを持っていたからです
and yet Paul was willing
to see the bigger picture.
それでも いろいろな要素を
考慮に入れました
He had strong feelings,
but at the same time,
うわさを聞かされていた
ユダヤ人たちはおそらく—
these Jews were probably new in the truth,
真理に新しい人たちでした
and Paul wanted to go as far as he could go
その人たちを
つまずかせないために—
so as not to stumble those new in the truth.
できる限りのことを
するつもりだったのです
Now the vow.
What was the vow?
ところでこの誓約ですが
ほとんどの学者の意見によると—
Most scholars agree that the vow
これはナジル人としての誓約
だったようです
was probably a Nazarite vow.
そうだとすると パウロには
慎重さが求められました
And if it was,
that was going to be tricky for Paul.
Because, you see, Nazarites
were required to offer a sin offering
ナジル人の誓約期間の終わりには—
罪の捧げ物をささげる必要が
あったからです
when their vow came to a completion.
Now, Paul would never have agreed to that.
パウロは この犠牲を
ささげることはできませんでした
It would have showed—
It would have shown disrespect
for the sacrifice of Christ.
キリストの犠牲に対する
不敬を示すことになるからです
So Paul and those four men
were going to have to be very careful
どの犠牲をささげ
どの犠牲はささげないかに関して—
about how far they would go
in the completion of this vow.
パウロとこの四人は
注意深く行動したことでしょう
And we can be sure
that they would never do anything
良心に責められることのない
決定をしたに違いありません
that would go against their conscience.
Now, we can see that on this occasion
この時パウロは
ユダヤ人をつまずかせないために—
Paul went a long way
できる限りのことをしたのです
so as not to stumble the Jews.
そのパウロがユダヤ人に合わせるのを
拒んだケースもあります
But on another occasion,
he refused to cater to the Jews.
We read about that in Galatians chapter 2.
ガラテア 2章に
そのことが書かれています
Let’s turn there.
Galatians chapter 2,
ガラテア 2章—
11から14節を読みましょう
and we’ll read verses 11-14.
Galatians 2:11-14:
“しかし ケファが
アンティオキアに来た時—”
“However, when Cephas came to Antioch,
“わたしは面と向かって
彼に抵抗しました”
“I resisted him face-to-face,
“彼には責めるべきところが
あったからです”
“because he was clearly in the wrong.
“ヤコブのもとから
ある人たちが来るまでは—”
“For before certain men from James arrived,
“諸国民の者たちと
一緒に食事をしていたのに—”
“he used to eat with people of the nations;
“彼らが来ると
割礼組の者たちへの恐れのために—”
“but when they arrived, he stopped doing this
and separated himself,
“身を引いて離れて行ったからです”
“fearing those of the circumcised class.
“残りのユダヤ人たちも
彼と共にこの虚偽に加わり—”
“The rest of the Jews also joined him
“in putting on this pretense,
“その結果
バルナバさえも—”
“so that even Barnabas
was led along with them in their pretense.
“彼らと共に
その虚偽に引かれて行きました”
“But when I saw
that they were not walking in step
“しかし 彼らが
良いたよりの真理にしたがって—”
“with the truth of the good news,
“まっすぐに
歩んでいないのを見た時—”
“I said to Cephas before them all:
“わたしはみんなの前で
ケファにこう言いました”
“‘If you, though you are a Jew,
live as the nations do and not as Jews do,
“「あなたは 自分では
ユダヤ人でありながら—”
how can you compel people of the nations
to live according to Jewish practice?’”
“諸国民のように生活し—”
“ユダヤ人がするようには
していないのに—”
So we see what was happening here.
“どうして諸国民の者たちに—”
“ユダヤ人の習わしにしたがって
生活することを強いているのですか」”
Up till the time when men from James
came down to Antioch,
ヤコブのもとから
ある人たちがやって来るまでは—
Peter and Barnabas
and the other Jewish Christians
アンティオキアにいた
ペテロとバルナバや—
were happily eating with the Gentiles.
他のユダヤ人のクリスチャンたちは—
But now men from James came down,
異邦人と喜んで
一緒に食事をしていたのに—
and suddenly Peter
その人たちが来ると
突然 ペテロは—
starts to separate himself from the Gentiles.
異邦人と交わるのをやめたのです
And, following his lead,
other Jewish Christians
begin doing the same thing.
他のユダヤ人のクリスチャンも
ペテロに倣ってしまいました
Now, who was probably new in the truth?
さてその時 真理に新しかったのは
だれでしたか？
In this case,
it was probably the Gentile Christians.
おそらく
異邦人のクリスチャンですね
In Acts 21, it was probably
the Jews who were newer in the truth
先ほどの使徒 21章で—
真理に新しかったのは
ユダヤ人でしたので—
and Paul didn’t want to stumble the Jews.
But at this point, Paul could not be
all things to all people.
パウロはその人たちを
つまずかせないようにしました
He couldn’t please the Jews;
でもアンティオキアでは ユダヤ人に
合わせることはしませんでした
he couldn’t please the men from James
and also please the Gentiles.
異邦人と
ユダヤ人の両方を—
満足させることが
不可能だったからです
He was either going to have to stumble
—if you will—
the men from James,
あえて言うなら—
or he was going
to have to stumble the Gentiles.
どちらかをつまずかせざる
を得ない状況だったのです
He had to make a choice.
難しい選択です
And so Paul made his choice.
パウロはどちらを選んだと
思われますか？
And what did he do about it?
He followed the advice
パウロは
ガラテア人への手紙の中で—
that he recorded
in this same book of Galatians.
自ら記した
アドバイスに従いました
Can you think of what that was?
どんなアドバイスでしたか？
ガラテア 6章には
何とあったでしょうか？
Galatians chapter 6
—what is it saying?
“たとえ人がそれと知らずに何か
誤った歩みをする場合でも”とあります
“If a man takes a false step
before he is aware of it.”
これは 良いたよりに従って歩んで
いなかったペテロに当てはまります
What did Paul say about Peter?
He was not walking in step
with the good news.
そして—
So Peter was taking a false step.
“霊的に資格のあるあなた方は”
つまりパウロのような人たちは—
“You who have spiritual qualifications,”
that would be Paul,
“温和な霊をもって
そのような人に—”
“try to readjust such a man
in a spirit of mildness.”
“再調整を施すことに努め” なさい
と続きます
And that’s what the apostle Paul did.
これがパウロの選択でした
Now, we love to pick on Peter.
さてこのように ペテロは
よく やり玉に挙げられますが—
But let’s give the poor man a break.
ペテロの正しい行ないも
思い起こしてみましょう
Let’s give him credit
for what he was doing right.
This was Antioch.
これもアンティオキアでの
出来事でした
Now, what do we know about Antioch?
アンティオキアは
律法を守ることについての論議が—
It was in Antioch when the whole matter
最初に起こった場所です
of keeping the Law blew up
in the first place.
論議を引き起こしたのは
だれでしたか？
And who was it
who were stirring things up in Antioch?
それは エルサレムから来た人たち
ヤコブのもとから来た人たちです
It was men from Jerusalem
—men from James.
Now, up until this point
その人たちがエルサレムから
アンティオキアにやって来て—
—Peter and Barnabas and the others—
they’re happily eating with the Gentiles
ペテロ バルナバ そして
他のユダヤ人のクリスチャンが—
until men from Jerusalem come down
異邦人と食事をしていると
言いがかりをつけたのです
and start stirring up trouble.
You kind of think
that if they’d stayed home once in a while
少しはエルサレムで静かにしていて
くれればいいのに……と思いますよね？
there would have been a lot less trouble
in the Christian congregation.
So Peter was doing the right thing
その人たちがやって来るまでは
ペテロは正しく行動していました
up until the men from James came down.
その人たちが
かなり批判的であることを—
Now, Peter knew
how critical men from James could be
ペテロは身にしみて感じていました
—or men from Jerusalem could be.
同じような状況に
遭遇したことがあったからです
You might say,
he’d seen that movie before
in 36 C.E.,
それは西暦36年
コルネリオの改宗 直後のことでした
just after the conversion of Cornelius.
Notice a detail at Acts 11:2, 3,
使徒 11章2, 3節から
詳細を調べてみましょう
and this might help us
to at least understand Peter’s concern,
ここを読むと
ペテロが何を心配して—
その人たちをつまずかせまいと
間違った努力をしたのか—
and perhaps misguided effort,
not to stumble the men from James.
その理由が分かるかもしれません
Acts 11:2, 3:
使徒 11章2, 3節
“So when Peter came up to Jerusalem,”
“それで ペテロが
エルサレムに上って来ると—”
this is in 33 C.E.,
これは西暦36年のことですが—
“the supporters of circumcision
began to criticize him, saying:
“割礼を支持する人々は
彼に対して言い争いを始め—”
“‘You went into the house of men
who were not circumcised
“彼が割礼を受けていない者たちの家に
入って一緒に食事をしたと言った”
and ate with them.’”
Well, Peter knew how sensitive Jews were
ユダヤ人が
異邦人と食事をすることに関して—
about eating with the Gentiles,
過敏だったのは事実です
but he was moved by the fear of man.
でもペテロはその事実を考慮して
行動したというよりは—
And the apostle Paul did right
to reprove him because, after all,
人への恐れに動かされていました
パウロに指摘されたように—
he was going to have to make a choice:
ペテロは異邦人のクリスチャンを
つまずかせないことを優先すべきでした
You stumble the Jews
or you stumble the Gentiles.
The lesson to take away:
この話の教訓は—
すべての人を満足させられない
時があるということです
There are times
when you can’t please everyone.
There are times when you
cannot be all things to all people.
あらゆる人に対して あらゆるものと
なれない時があるのです
Our young people have to realize that.
特に若い人たちは
このことを覚えておくべきです
You have to take a stand for what is right
正しい決定をしたなら—
and let the chips fall where they may.
他の人から何を言われようと
気に留めないことです
Now, you have to appreciate the wisdom
イエスがパウロを選んで
諸国民への使徒とされた—
that Jesus used in selecting Paul
その見識の高さには
驚かされます
as an apostle to the nations.
A note to the elders:
長老たちへのアドバイスがあります
Paul was flexible.
パウロは柔軟でした
He didn’t insist on his own ideas
しっかりした自分の見解を
持っていたとしても—
even when he felt strongly about a matter,
それにこだわって無駄な議論を
引き起こすことはありませんでした
and he didn’t create unnecessary issues.
様々な要素を
考慮に入れました
Paul looked at the big picture.
実に立派な手本です
What a marvelous example for us.
パウロは謙遜だったので
この奉仕に うってつけの人物でした
And we can say that humble Paul
was the right man for the job.